A masterpiece of modern horror.
The Shining is a horror, thriller film directed by Stanley Kubrick.
Jack Torrance accepts a caretaker job at the Overlook Hotel, where he, along with his wife Wendy
and their son Danny, must live isolated from the rest of the world for the winter.
But they aren't prepared for the madness that lurks within.
Jack Torrance, played by Jack Nicholson.
Wendy Torrance, played by Shelley Duvall.
Danny, played by Danny Lloyd.
Hallorann, played by Scatman Crothers.
Ullman, played by Barry Nelson.
Grady, played by Philip Stone.
The Shining is a 1980 psychological horror film produced and directed by
Stanley Kubrick and co-written with novelist Diane Johnson.
It is based on Stephen King's 1977 novel and stars Jack Nicholson,
Shelley Duvall, Danny Lloyd and Scatman Crothers.
The film presents the descent into insanity of a recovering alcoholic and aspiring novelist who takes a
job as winter caretaker for a mountain resort hotel with his wife and clairvoyant son.
Production took place almost exclusively in England at EMI
Elstree Studios, with sets based on real locations.
Kubrick often worked with a small crew, which allowed him to do many
takes, sometimes to the exhaustion of the actors and staff.
The then-new Steadicam mount was used to shoot several scenes, giving
the film an innovative and immersive look and feel.
The film was released in the United States on May 23, 1980, by Warner Bros., and in the United
Kingdom on October 2 by Columbia Pictures through Columbia-EMI-Warner Distributors.
There were several versions for theatrical releases, each of which was cut
shorter than the preceding cut; about 27 minutes was cut in total.
Reactions to the film at the time of its release were mixed; King
criticized the film due to its deviations from the novel.
The film received two controversial nominations at the 1st Golden Raspberry Awards in 1981—Worst Director and Worst
Actress—the latter of which was later rescinded in 2022 due to Kubrick's alleged treatment of Duvall on set.
The Shining has since been critically reappraised and is often
cited as one of the best horror films ever made.
It was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the Library of
Congress as being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant" in 2018.
A sequel titled Doctor Sleep, based on King's 2013 novel of the
same name, was adapted to film and released in 2019.
The film explores themes of hotel, new year's eve, child
abuse, based on novel or book, isolation.
The tone is intense and dark and mind_bending.